<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

	<properties>
		<title>OWL specification</title>
		<author email="paolo.contessi@studio.unibo.it">Paolo Contessi</author>
	</properties>

	<body>

		<section name="OWL specification">
			<p>
				<strong>OWL (Web Ontology Language)</strong> is a tool for specifying semantics and defining knowledge models. 
				It can be said that OWL represents 
				an extension of <a href="rdfs-spec.html">RDF Schema</a>, which provides <em>more expressive
				power</em>, but, in order to provide that power, it's computational complexity raises and in <em>some
				cases</em> becomes a <em>not-decidable problem</em>.
			</p>
			<p>
				With the aim of limiting this problem from the whole specification, called <em>OWL-Full</em>, some subsets and
				profiles has been defined, providing limited versions of the language, otherwise useless.
				A diffuse example is <strong>OWL-DL</strong>, named after Description Logic because it provides 
				many of the capabilities of description logic, an important subset of first-order logic; other examples are
				OWL-EL, which is designed to perform consistency checks and instance-class mapping in polinomial-time, and 
				OWL-QL, which is designed to enable the satisfiability of conjunctive queries in logspace with respect to 
				the number of assertions in the queried knowledge base.
			</p>
			<p>
				<em>OWL is merely an ontology language; it is not an application</em>. As such, OWL alone doesn't really do anything, 
				but combined with a reasoner like <a href="pellet-reasoner.html">Pellet</a>, represent the 
				added value against other approaches for exchanging information. A <strong>reasoning engine</strong> (or reasoner) is 
				a system that <em>infers new information based on the contents of a knowledge base</em>. This can be accomplished using rules 
				and a rule engine, triggers on a database or RDF store, decision trees, tableau algorithms, or even programmatically 
				using hard-coded business logic. 
				Many Semantic Web frameworks perform inference using rules-based reasoning engines. <em>These engines combine the assertions 
				contained in a knowledge base with a set of logical rules in order to derive assertions or perform actions</em>. 
				Rules comprise two parts, modeling an if-then statement. The first part is the condition for the rule, 
				and the second part is conclusion of the rule. <em>Rules can be used to express much of the semantics of OWL and as a tool 
				for users to express arbitrary relationships that cannot otherwise be modeled in OWL</em>. 
			</p>
			<p>
				An ontology purpose is letting a concept be machine-understandable. Generally these concepts are spread in the World Wide Web,
				so the knowledge base (expressed in RDF) is considered distributed. In the same way RDF supports distribution, OWL should support it too;
				this is called <strong>distributed knowledge</strong>. To provide a foundation on which to make valid inferences in this model, 
				we must make two important assumptions: 
			</p>
			<ul>
				<li><strong>Open World Assumption</strong>: not knowing whether a statement is explicitly true does not imply that the statement is false; 
					in this context new information must always be additive. It can be contradictory, but it cannot remove previously asserted information.</li>
				<li><strong>No Unique Names Assumption</strong>: it is unreasonable to assume that everyone is using the same URI to identify a specific resource; 
					<em>unless explicitly stated otherwise, you cannot assume that resources that are identified by different URIs are different</em>.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>
				An ontology, expressed in OWL-Full version 2.0, is composed by:
			</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Ontology header</li>
				<li>Classes and individuals</li>
				<li>Properties: object and datatype</li>
				<li>Annotations</li>
				<li>Datatypes: standard or restricted</li>
			</ul>
			
			<subsection name="Ontology header">
				<p>
					An ontology header is <strong>a resource that represents the ontology itself</strong>, containing comments, labels, versioning and a list of
					the imported ontologies, which is very important because instructs the reasoner to refer to them to in order to comprehend the expressed concepts and
					relationships.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Classes and individuals">
				<p>
					An OWL class is a special kind of resource that represents a set of resources that share common characteristics or are similar in some way. 
					A resource that is a member of a class is called an individual and represents an instance of that class.
				</p>
				<p>
					Like in <a href="rdfs-spec.html">RDF Schema</a> two classes might be one the subclass of the other; but, when not explicitly stated, a class is 
					automatically subclass of <strong><tt>owl:Thing</tt></strong> (similarly to OOP with Object). In OWL <tt>owl:Nothing</tt> is also defined: it is
					the subclass of every class, so specialized that it has literally <em>no individuals</em> (its an empty class).
				</p>
				<p>
					Another relevant concept is <strong>class equivalence</strong>, in fact in general two classes, even if has the same local name, may express different ideas.
					Two classes are equivalent only if explicitly stated in the ontology, otherwise they aren't; extension does not imply equivalence. 
				</p>
				<p>
					The individuals of a class may be uniquely identified by a subset of its properties (other than by URIreference); these properties determine a <em>key</em>,
					which can be enumerated in a special property called <strong><tt>owl:hasKey</tt></strong>.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Properties">
				<p>
					In OWL properties can be of two types, based on the resources used:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li><strong><tt>owl:DatatypeProperty</tt></strong>: these properties as a literal object</li>
					<li><strong><tt>owl:ObjectProperty</tt></strong>: these properties state a relation between two individuals</li>
				</ul>
				<p>
					The predicates <tt>rdf:domain</tt> and <tt>rdf:range</tt> globally define the class membership for property subject and object.
					This implies that a class which does not match with membership definition cannot use that properties, avoiding unwanted and unpredicted inferences;  
					if ex:name is a property for ex:Mammal and we use the same property for ex:Institution we automatically assume that an institution is a mammal, which is false. 
				</p>
				<p>
					As with classes, properties can be arranged into taxonomies using the property <tt>rdfs:subPropertyOf</tt>. <strong>Be careful that asserting that <tt>property2</tt>
					is sub-property of <tt>property1</tt> implies that two resources in relationship by <tt>property2</tt> are also related by <tt>property1</tt>.</strong>
					Similar to <tt>owl:Thing</tt> and <tt>owl:Nothing</tt>, <tt>owl:top(Object|Data)Property</tt> and <tt>owl:bottom(Object|Data)Property</tt> represents the most general
					an most specific properties of the taxonomy. 
				</p>
				<p>
					Other features of properties, descending from mathematics, are:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>Inverse Properties</strong>: a property state the inverse relationship stated by another property (e.g. if A owns B then B isOwnedy A)</li>
					<li><strong>Disjoint Properties</strong>: if two resources are related by propX then they cannot be related by propY (e.g. if A hasFather B then not(A hasMother B))</li>
					<li><strong>Property Chains</strong>: using a couple or more properties two define a new one (e.g. if A hasFather B and B hasBrother C then A hasUncle C)</li>
					<li><strong>Symmetric, Reflexive, Transitive Properties</strong>: like in mathematic relationships</li>
					<li><strong>(Inverse) Functional Property</strong>: each subject (object) is related to only one object (subject)</li>
				</ul>
				
				<h4>Negative Property Assertion</h4>
				<p>
					While in general a property is stating in order to assert that something is true, it is also possible to define the opposite (that if stated then something is false)
					using the type <tt>owl:NegativeProperty</tt>. The following example models that <em>is not true that ex:Daisy ex:hasOwner ex:Amber</em>. 
				</p>
				<source>
@prefix ex: &lt;http://example.org/&gt; . 
... 

[] rdf:type owl:NegativePropertyAssertion; 
	owl:sourceIndividual ex:Daisy; 	
	owl:assertionProperty ex:hasOwner; 
	owl:targetIndividual ex:Amber.</source>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Annotations">
				<p>
					Annotations are statements that describe resources using annotation properties. Annotation properties are semantics-free properties.
				</p>
				<p>
					Common examples of annotations are: <tt>rdf:label</tt>, <tt>rdf:comment</tt> and <tt>rdf:versionInfo</tt>. 
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Datatypes">
				<p>
					Datatypes represent ranges of data values that are identified using URIs. 
					OWL allows you to use a number of predefined datatypes, most of which are defined in the XML Schema Definition (xsd) namespace.
				</p>
				<p>
					Otherwise OWL allows the definition of custom datatypes, in two ways:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>by <strong>Datatypes Restriction</strong>, which consists in defining a new <tt>rdfs:Datatype</tt> and specifying:
					<ul>
						<li><strong><tt>owl:onDatatype</tt></strong>: a primitive datatype</li>
						<li><strong><tt>owl:withRestrictions</tt></strong>: a list of facets (constraints) on data value, length, char pattern and so on</li>
					</ul>
					</li>
					<li>by <strong>Definition in terms of other Datatypes</strong>, in particular by intersection or union of a bunch of datatypes (primitive or custom)</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Property Restriction">
				<p>
					A property restriction describes the class of individuals that meet the specified property-based conditions. The restriction is declared 
					using the construct <tt>owl:Restriction</tt>, and the property to which the restriction refers is identified using the property <tt>owl:onProperty</tt>.
				</p>
				<p>
					Restrictions are applied to a particular class by stating that the class is either a subclass (<tt>rdfs:subClassOf</tt>) or the equivalent class 
					(<tt>owl:equivalentClass</tt>) of the restriction. In the <em>former</em> case <em>all members of the class must meet the conditions</em> specified by the 
					restriction, in the <em>latter</em> case class members must meet the conditions of the restriction and <em>any individual who meets the conditions</em> 
					of the restriction <em>is implicitly a member of the class</em> (restriction specifies conditions that are not only necessary but also sufficient).
				</p>
				<p>
					<strong>N.B.: The OWL specification requires that restriction cannot be named and must be defined using anonymous resources.</strong> 
					This is a reasonable condition because restrictions are relevant only to the context of the class in which they are defined and never need to be referred to.
				</p>
				<p>
					There are three types of Property Restrictions: Value restriction, Cardinality restriction and Qualified cardinality description, which is a combination of
					the former two.
				</p>
				
				<h4>Value restriction</h4>
				<p>
					There are three types of value restriction, whose difference is relative to the number of occurrences of the restricted property that must fit the constraint. 
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li><strong><tt>owl:allValuesFrom</tt></strong> states that each occurrence of the property (if any) must have the object value in the specified range</li>
					<li><strong><tt>owl:someValuesFrom</tt></strong> states that at least one occurrence of the property must have the object value in the specified range</li>
					<li><strong><tt>owl:hasValue</tt></strong> states that an occurrence of the property must have the specified object value</li>
				</ul>
				<source>
@prefix ex: &lt;http://www.example.org/&gt;

# owl:allValuesFrom example
# This restriction defines a class, ex:CallableEntities, whose name have a range of xsd:string
<strong>ex:CallableEnties rdfs:subClassOf [
	rdf:type owl:Restriction;
	rdf:onProperty ex:name;
	owl:allValuesFrom xsd:string
	].</strong>

# owl:someValuesFrom example
# This restriction defines a class whose members extends a serializeable class
<strong>ex:SerializeableClass rdfs:subClassOf [
	rdf:type owl:Restriction;
	rdf:onProperty ex:extends;
	owl:someValuesFrom ex:SerializeableClass;
	].</strong>

# owl:hasValue example
# This restriction define a class of mammals whose owner is ex:Ryan
<strong>ex:Mammal rdf:type owl:Class. 
ex:hasOwner rdf:type owl:ObjectProperty.

ex:PetsOfRyan rdf:type owl:Class; 
	rdfs:subClassOf ex:Mammal; 
	rdfs:subClassOf[
	rdf:type owl:Restriction;
	owl:onProperty ex:hasOwner; 
	owl:hasValue ex:Ryan
	].</strong></source>

				<p>
					There's also another type of value restriction, <strong><tt>owl:SelfRestriction</tt></strong>, 
					which states that value of the property is the subject itself. <tt>owl:SelfRestriction</tt> is an alternative to <tt>owl:Restriction</tt>.
				</p>
				<source>
# owl:SelfRestriction example.
<strong>ex:cleans rdf:type owl:ObjectProperty.</strong>

# Self cleaners are all individuals who clean themselves (range is implicit) 
<strong>ex:SelfCleaner rdf:type owl:Class; 
	owl:equivalentClass [ 
		rdf:type owl:SelfRestriction;
		owl:onProperty ex:cleans
		].</strong></source>
				
				<h4>Cardinality restriction</h4>
				<p>
					This type of restriction provides a way to specify how many occurrences of the property are required. 
					This can be done using the following predicates (obviously N >= 0):
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li><strong><tt>owl:minCardinality</tt></strong>, #occs &gt;= N</li>
					<li><strong><tt>owl:maxCardinality</tt></strong>, #occs &lt;= N</li>
					<li><strong><tt>owl:cardinality</tt></strong>, #occs == N</li>
				</ul>
				<source>
@prefix ex: &lt;http://example.org/&gt;.
 
ex:Person rdfs:subClassOf [ 
	rdf:type owl:Restriction; 
	owl:onProperty ex:name; 
	<strong>owl:cardinality 1</strong>
	].
</source>
				
				<h4>Qualified Cardinality restriction</h4>
				<p>
					It represents a way to define both cardinality and type. It is useful to model a system composed by some components
					and you need to assert that there are N components of type X, M components of type Y and so on.
				</p>
				<source>
# This examples models that a person has 2 biological parents:
# a male and a female.
@prefix ex: &lt;http://example.org/&gt;. 

ex:Person rdf:type owl:Class; 
ex:Male rdf:type owl:Class;
	rdfs:subClassOf ex:Person.
ex:Female rdf:type owl:Class;
	rdfs:subClassOf ex:Person. 

ex:hasBiologicalParent rdf:type owl:ObjectProperty.

ex:Person rdfs:subClassOf [ 
		rdf:type owl:Restriction; 
		owl:cardinality 2; 
		owl:onProperty ex:hasBiologicalParent 
		]; 
	rdfs:subClassOf [
		rdf:type owl:Restriction;
		<strong>owl:qualifiedCardinality 1;</strong>
		owl:onProperty ex:hasBiologicalParent; 
		owl:onClass ex:Male 
		];
	rdfs:subClassOf [ 
		rdf:type owl:Restriction; 
		<strong>owl:qualifiedCardinality 1;</strong>
		owl:onProperty ex:hasBiologicalParent; 
		owl:onClass ex:Female 
		].</source>
			</subsection>
		</section>
		<section name="Advanced Class Description">
		<p>
			OWL provides a few more methods for describing classes.
		</p>
		<subsection name="Enumerating Class Membership">
			<p>
				In some cases you may be interested in the enumeration of the only individuals that can be members of a defined class. 
				This can be done with the predicate <tt>owl:oneOf</tt>.
			</p>
			<source>
@prefix ex: &lt;http://example.org/&gt;. 

ex:Daisy rdf:type ex:Canine. 

ex:Cubby rdf:type ex:Canine.
ex:Amber rdf:type ex:Canine. 
ex:London rdf:type ex:Canine.

# Each friend of Daisy's is explicitly included in this class 
ex:FriendsOfDaisy rdf:type owl:Class; 
	<strong>owl:oneOf ( 
		ex:Cubby 
		ex:Amber 
		ex:London 
	)</strong>.</source>
		
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="Set operators">
			<p>
				In order to define new classes it could be useful to specify that a class is the union, intersection or complementary of two or more classes.
				That's why <tt>owl:unionOf</tt>, <tt>owl:intersectionOf</tt>, <tt>owl:complementaryOf</tt> exists. An example of each one is reported in the following.  
			</p>
			<source>
@prefix ex: %lt;http://example.org/%gt;. 

# Example 1: intersection of 
ex:PetsOfRyan rdf:type owl:Class; 
	owl:intersectionOf (
		ex:Mammal 
		[ 
			rdf:type owl:Restriction; 
			owl:onProperty ex:hasOwner;
			owl:hasValue ex:Ryan 
		] 
	). 

# Example 2: union of 
ex:isFriendsWith rdf:type owl:ObjectProperty.

ex:FriendsOfRyan rdf:type ex:Class; 
	owl:unionOf ( 
		[ 
			rdf:type owl:Class; 
			owl:oneOf ( 
				ex:Daisy 
			) 
		] 
		ex:FriendsOfDaisy 
		[ 
			rdf:type owl:Restriction;
			owl:onProperty ex:isFriendsWith; 
			owl:hasValue ex:Ryan 
		] 
	). 
	
#Example 3: complement of 
ex:EnemiesOfRyan rdf:type owl:Class; 
	owl:complementOf ex:FriendsOfRyan.</source>
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="Disjointed Class">
			<p>
				Similarly to properties case it is possible to define that 
				<strong>if an individual is instance of a class it cannot be also instance of another class, called disjointed</strong>.
			</p>
			<source>
@prefix ex: &lt;http://example.org/&gt;. 

# canine and human are disjoint classes 
<strong>ex:Canine owl:disjointWith ex:Human.</strong></source>
		<p>
			In order to reduce time spent in defining disjunctions (which is considerable augmenting model size), some shorthands has been defined:
		</p>
		<ul>
			<li><strong><tt>owl:AllDisjointedClasses</tt></strong> is an anonymous resource whose <tt>owl:members</tt> 
			property refers to a list of classes, all subclasses of the same class, that will be considered disjointed.</li>
			<li><strong><tt>owl:disjointUnionOf</tt></strong> let directly define a class as the union of a list of disjointed classes
				<ul>
					<li><em>The drawback to the use of a disjoint union to define a superclass is that any future attempt to 
					incorporate a new subclass will require you to redefine the disjoint union to include the new subclass.</em></li>
				</ul>
			</li>
		</ul> 
		<p>
			Let's present some examples:
		</p>
		<source>
@prefix ex: &lt;http://example.org/&gt;. 

# --> Example 1
# canine and human are disjoint classes 
ex:Canine owl:disjointWith ex:Human. 

# --> Example 2
ex:Animal rdf:type owl:Class.
 
ex:Bird rdf:type owl:Class; 
	rdfs:subClassOf ex:Animal. 
ex:Lizard rdf:type owl:Class; 
	rdfs:subClassOf ex:Animal. 
ex:Feline rdf:type owl:Class; 
	rdfs:subClassOf ex:Animal. 

# Each of the classes is pair-wise disjoint 
_: rdf:type owl:AllDisjointClasses; 
	owl:members ( ex:Bird ex:Lizard ex:Feline ex:Canine ).

# --> Example 3
# Each of the classes is pair-wise disjoint 
# and Animal is the union of those classes 
ex:Animal owl:disjointUnionOf ( 
	ex:Bird 
	ex:Lizard 
	ex:Feline 
	ex:Canine 
). </source>
		</subsection>
		</section>
		<section name="Equivalence in OWL">
			<p>
				At this point the last thing to be told is how OWL states the equivalence between two entities.
			</p>
			<p>
				There are several ways of defining an equivalence and each one of them involves different type of entites:
			</p>
			<dl>
				<dt>Equivalence among Individuals</dt>
				<dd><br />
					<strong>"Equal":</strong>
					<ul>
						<li>Useful to suggest that two URIreferences, even if different, are relative to the same individual</li>
						<li>Stated with <strong><tt>owl:sameAs</tt></strong> predicate
						<source>
&lt;mailto:rblace@bbn.com&gt; owl:sameAs &lt;http://example.org/people#rblace&gt;.</source>
						</li>
					</ul><br />
					<strong>"Not-equal":</strong>
					<ul>
						<li>Useful to suggest that two individuals have nothing in common</li>
						<li>Stated with <strong><tt>owl:differentFrom</tt></strong> predicate</li>
						<li>
							In order to reduce the number of statements <strong><tt>owl:AllDifferent</tt></strong> can be used (like in disjoint classes).
							<source>
[] rdf:type owl:AllDifferent; 
	owl:distinctMembers ( ex:Daisy ex:Cubby ex:Amber ex:London ).</source>
							<p>This property is very important, because the combination of the open world assumption and the no unique names assumption results in an
							environment where there are very few situations in which you can assume that resources identified by different URIs are different.</p>
						</li>
					</ul><br />
				</dd>
				<dt>Equivalence among Classes</dt>
				<dd>
					<ul>
						<li>Causes two classes to be considered as a single resource</li>
						<li>Stated with <strong><tt>owl:equivalentClass</tt></strong> predicate</li>
					</ul>
				</dd>
				<dt>Equivalence among Properties</dt>
				<dd>
					<ul>
						<li>When you assert that two properties are equivalent, the property descriptions are combined. Every statement that uses one of the properties
							as a predicate implicitly exists with the other equivalent property as a predicate as well</li>
						<li>Stated with <strong><tt>owl:equivalentProperty</tt></strong> predicate</li>
					</ul>
				</dd>
			</dl>
		</section>
	</body>

</document>