<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

	<properties>
		<title>Semantic Web Technologies</title>
		<author email="paolo.contessi@studio.unibo.it">Paolo Contessi</author>
	</properties>

	<body>

		<section name="Semantic Web Technologies">

			<p>
				This section provides an overview of semantic web domain. In fact
				it reports all relevant information regarding W3C specification and
				main technologies which can be used to satisfy requirements.
			</p>

			<subsection name="W3C specification">
				<table>
					<tr>
						<th width="15%">Resource</th>
						<th>Description</th>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>
							<a href="rdf-spec.html">RDF</a>
						</td>
						<td>
							Resource Description Framework. Basic language which is
							possible to state a set of information about some resources with.
						</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>
							<a href="rdfs-spec.html">RDF Schema</a>
						</td>
						<td>
							Language, based on RDF, which can model a relationships
							between classes, and properties: extension, domain and range.
						</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>
							<a href="owl-spec.html">OWL</a>
						</td>
						<td>
							Web Ontology Language. A powerful language which extends
							RDFSchema providing more expressive power. The full specification
							is not decidable in general, that's why a number of profiles or
							subsets, that give up some expressive power in exchange for more
							attractive and feasible computational characteristics, has been
							defined.
						</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>
							<a href="sparql-spec.html">SPARQL</a>
						</td>
						<td>
							SPARQL is the standard query language over a RDF Store, meant
							to retrieve data according to specific requests without
							modifications. In order to provide write features SPARQL Update has been defined.
							Its syntax and principles recalls SQL.
						</td>
					</tr>
				</table>
				<p>
					All information reported in this subsection has been taken from:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>
						<strong>W3C specification</strong>
						(see
						<a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-primer/">http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-primer/</a>
						and related documents)
					</li>
					<li>
						<strong>Semantic Web Programming</strong>
						- J. Hebler, M. Fisher, R. Blace, A. Perez-Lopez - Wiley
						Publishing Inc.
					</li>
				</ul>
				<p>
					<strong>N.B.: A new SPARQL working draft has been submitted (v. 1.1). After February, 6 2012 this version may become the recommended one!</strong>
				</p>
			</subsection>

			<subsection name="Technologies">
				<table>
					<tr>
						<th width="15%">Resource</th>
						<th>Description</th>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>
							<a href="jena-framework.html">Jena</a>
						</td>
						<td>
							Jena is a Java framework for building Semantic Web
							applications, which provides a collection of tools and Java
							libraries designed to help semantic web and linked-data apps
							development.
						</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>
							<a href="pellet-reasoner.html">Pellet</a>
						</td>
						<td>
							Pellet is an OWL 2 reasoner, so provides reasoning services
							for OWL ontologies for all ontology-based data management
							applications.
						</td>
					</tr>
				</table>
			</subsection>
		</section>
	</body>

</document>